collagen is one of those proteins that's
had a lot of indecision surrounding its
Effectiveness especially in relation to
skin but I'd like to spend some time
discussing some new sides on collagen in
our joints especially for middle-aged
and older individuals in a recent study
introduced to me by yet another
physionic Insider researchers identified
two things that supposedly encourage
collagen synthesis in relation to our
joints and since collagen synthesis is
important for joint health because the
extracellular Matrix the makeup of our
joints including tendons and ligaments
is largely made of collagen it's
important to raise it when possible so
what are these two factors and what did
the study actually find and what can we
take away from this study this is the
study and as you can tell by the title
the two factors are resistance training
and another is consumable collagen but
there's as usual a lot of nuance on both
that we'll need to discuss quickly the
researchers gave the same participants
either a placebo a low dose of collagen
or a high dose of collagen including
vitamin C in all conditions so each
participant acted as their own control
known as a repeated measures design they
consumed each masked drink on different
days and then performed four sets of 10
repetitions of leg press the researchers
then took blood samples for the next 6
hours you can imagine that these people
were pretty hungry after all that I mean
considering that they came and fasted
and then they had a measly collagen
drink and then they worked out and then
they had to stay in the lab and refrain
from eating for another 6 hours not so
fun anyway what did the researchers find
well two things one they measured blood
P1 andp levels that's the abbreviation
for procollagen or an immature form of
collagen now typically your cells
generate collagen in a procollagen form
Pro it in the GGI apparatus which is an
organel found inside most cells and then
secreted out of the cell to be acted on
by a series of enzymes that convert it
to mature nonpr collagen it's almost
like the pro label is actually
amateur this is an elegant experiment
because the researchers are able to
measure newly synthesized collagen
directly so if procollagen labeled as P1
NP goes up that's an indication of more
of this collagen synthesis
and we see that here we have P1 and P
blood levels on the vertical axis and
time on the horizontal note that the
minus one is the Baseline measure
completely fasted and before consuming
one of the three drinks and anything
after zero is after drinking the
collagen and after doing the leg press
so to orient you the black line is the
placebo the no collagen and the bluish
line is the low collagen dose and the
pink line is the high collagen dose
clearly although also confirmed by the
correct statistics p1np was increased in
both collagen conditions indicating
collagen synthesis now if you think
about this a bit longer you might note
that I mentioned resistance training
increases collagen synthesis yet here we
don't see any Improvement I'll discuss
that shortly because the researchers
address that too first let me show you
another measure and then I'd like to add
some more context to all this including
a problem that you may have missed in
this data that I already showed you uh
beyond the flatline on resistance
training that is another measure the
researchers were interested in is
collagen breakdown remember we covered
collagen synthesis so the production but
this might be a moot point if collagen
breakdown also occurs especially from
strenuous activity like resistance
training for that the researchers looked
at a collagen degradation marker called
beta CTX here's those data on the left
we have the same line graph over time
and on the right we have the area under
the curve or the total effect what's
striking here is that Cen
supplementation made no difference on
collagen breakdown but that's not a bad
thing because all three conditions
experienced a reduction compared to
Baseline that means that resistance
training is likely the greater driver of
reducing collagen breakdown not colron
supplementation itself which I think is
a pretty neat finding if it holds true
okay quickly there's some information
information comparing protein against
collagen as well as optimal dosing for
maximum effect I'll be covering that in
the extended version of this video
including different independently tested
Brands if you're interested along with
access to all my work it's included with
the physionic Insiders which is a Linked
In the description okay how do we put
all this together and what does this
mean for you well let me address the
resistance training aspect first the
researchers speculate that the reason
resistance training had no effect at
raising blood procollagen levels is
because the total amount of work
performed was small in addition they
mention many other studies including
this one indicate resistance training
typically increases collagen related
protein synthesis it's also possible
because this study was in middle-aged
men that other studies are able to show
an effect because they were in younger
participants either way there's more
evidence indicating resistance training
does raise collagen synthesis than not
and one more thing that I mentioned a
problem with the data keep in mind we've
been focused on blood levels of
procollagen but that does not speak to
Joint collagen production directly now
before your eyes snap to the title this
video there are two points to be made in
favor of this being joint related
collagen synthesis one collagen type one
the one that we've been looking at is
largely found in the joints in the
pendant and the ligaments as mentioned
before still it is also found in other
areas of the body so this Blood measure
is not ideal even if it is suggestive
however to in this other study the
researchers directly probed connective
tissue like that in joints and assess
that there is still a likely increase in
synthesis confirming the more
generalized results that we see in this
first study now to be transparent I say
likely because the result results of
this study did not reach statistical
significance but the study wasn't
powered to detect an effect on
connective tissue synthesis and the
results were still very close to
significant that isn't to mention that
other studies indicate effects aside
from the ones that we've been focused on
now what do we take away from this two
things one that cogent supplementation
seems to increase joint related although
not exclusive collagen synthesis truly
supercharging it over 50% more than when
not consuming it I would like to see
more robust measures like actual size
and function changes in a joint through
long-term studies but this is a solid
First Step so collagen consumption seems
to work at increasing collagen
production now two resistance training
facilitates the increase in joint
collagen production and this was also
more directly shown in this study
although some of the nuances on volume
intensity duration of exposure uh need
to be detailed in future studies but we
don't need to stop here because guess
what I have more on this topic right
here if Thou Art so inclined I'll speak
with you over there
[Music]